<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-01T11:56:21-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/</id><title type="html">TMT Controversy</title><subtitle>Jekyll version of the Massively theme by HTML5UP</subtitle><entry><title type="html">TMT in the Eyes of Local People in Hawaii – Opinion</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/TMT-In-The-Eyes-Of-Local-People-in-Hawaii-Opinion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TMT in the Eyes of Local People in Hawaii – Opinion" /><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-31T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/TMT-In-The-Eyes-Of-Local-People-in-Hawaii-–-Opinion</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/TMT-In-The-Eyes-Of-Local-People-in-Hawaii-Opinion/">&lt;p&gt;I’d like to preface that this will be an opinionated piece based on what I’ve learned from this project. This is from the perspective of someone who is not only from Hawaii, but much of my knowledge on the topic has been from researching this controversy in the past few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of creating and researching for this project, I’ve been really put into my place and forced to think about this controversy from a different point of view. I don’t think that is something that we have to do very often. Though many are facing injustice everywhere, it can be hard to put yourself into the shoes of those people. In Hawaii, majority of the population is Asian, which I personally identify as. I am a 5th generation Japanese and Chinese American, middle class, and went to a private school for most of my schooling. I’m not very in touch with my culture not only because of how removed I am from my homeland, but also because the Hawaii (different than Hawaiian) culture is very much a melting pot of all those who came to work on the plantations. I’ve always prided myself in this. In the sense of we don’t really see race and ethnicities here. You’ll hear about how many of us are against haoles (white people) as they usually come here with no respect for the land, but we mostly stick together as locals. It’s not uncommon for people to only see Hawaii as a tourist destination because that is what our government has put at the forefront of our economy which means that we have to protect our home from these types of outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though we are together at that front, it is many times hard for us to understand all of the hardships the Native Hawaiians have faced. We may hear about it, but if we are not personally affected, it’s unlikely people will care. We acknowledge that what was done to them was wrong, but in the end, it has no effect on us as non-Hawaiians. I tried to compare it to something in my own life, in my own culture. I thought, “If it was Japanese sacred land, would I care?” I would definitely think it was disrespectful, but I’m unsure if I would have gone out to protest on the matter. I don’t think this means that the Hawaiians are overreacting, if anything it just proves what I said earlier, that we just are not as connected to our culture as they are. Another thing that is important to note is that there was never a need for a cultural renaissance for Asian cultures unlike than the Hawaiians. We were never put in the position by the government (other than the Japanese in Hawaii during WWII) where we were having laws to prohibit us from practicing our culture. This says so much as we Asians came in as outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve felt a lot of frustration while researching for this project because of the blatant disregard and disrespect for the Hawaiian culture not only from those outsiders that we have been fighting off for years, but also those within the state. There are way more TMT supporters within Hawaii than I ever would have thought. How could this be? We have spent all of this time taking pride in our islands and where we come from, but once the Hawaiians stood up for something that was unrelated to the rest of us, there was silence. I’m not sure there is a good answer out there for this; “good” meaning justifiable. I think it comes down to the rest of the island not being educated. The rest of the us don’t care to be educated on the topic. Ignorance is bliss. I think that this is a commonality in many controversies. Some people would rather stay out of it rather than do the research or even pay attention when the news is on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I am unsure that there will be a significant change. We can’t change how people view this controversy, but we are all doing our best to educate those around us. Whether they remember everything we said, or just one thing. Regardless, it’s more than they knew before. I hope that those who read through this project have a better understanding of the Hawaiian culture, the injustice they have faced in the past and why Maunakea is important to them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Opinion piece on TMT controversy</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kawais Q&amp;amp;A</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Kawais-QnA/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kawais Q&amp;A" /><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-29T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Kawais-QnA</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Kawais-QnA/">&lt;p&gt;My name is Kawaiuluhonua Olafaʻapelepele Scanlan, but I go by Kawai for short. I was born and raised in Honolulu on ʻOahu. I am about 1/8 Native Hawaiian on my Mom’s side and about 1/8 Samoan on my dad’s. The rest is a mix of Irish, English, and Portuguese. I recently graduated from Scripps College, earning my BA in Psychology with a minor in Native American/Indigenous Studies (NAIS). Next fall, I will be attending Richardson School of Law at the University of Hawaiʻi at Mānoa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Living in Hawaii, did you feel any sort of bias against Hawaiians in your own life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a young age, I knew the history of the overthrow and all that so I was well aware of the biases against Hawaiians and also the biases against haole (mostly White) people. Kids in elementary school would make fun of my name sometimes because it wasn’t English. Kids would also tease me about being haole. But my grandpa, who wasn’t Hawaiian, but Samoan, would tell me stories about anti-Samoan racism that he grew up with here. He would tell my brother and I not to worry because it was badass to be who we are, and we were related to him and other cool people, so it didn’t matter. I feel like I was hyperaware of racial bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you give a little background on your childhood and growing up with the Hawaiian culture?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first school I ever went to was Punana Leo o Kawaihaʻo, a small Hawaiian immersion school. In order to really learn the language, the school required that the parents also enroll in a course so that the language could be spoken at home. My younger brother went there, too, so for the first chunk of my life, we were speaking ʻōlelo Hawaiʻi at home. Both my parents were growing up in Hawaiʻi in the 1970’s when the renaissance was going on, so they were really keen on making sure that my brother and I grew up with the culture that had been nearly lost. Since elementary school though, I had to learn English in school so we stopped speaking Hawaiian at home, and I eventually lost my ability to speak. But culturally speaking, I very much have a Hawaiian lens. All my values and my religion is Native Hawaiian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The thing about TMT that frustrates you the most?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing about TMT that frustrates me the most is the argument that “Hawaiians don’t believe in science.” This argument is just classic colonialism and it makes me angry. It’s things like this that perpetuate the narrative that Hawaiians are a people of the past and consequently Native epistemologies cannot exist in a world that is ruled by Western science. In actuality, Hawaiians are and have always been scientists, just not by-the-book Western science. The kumulipo, for example, is a chant about the origin story of Hawaiian people and it describes exactly what White scientists took centuries to figure out. It talks about how first the earth was dark, and there were only little bugs or bacteria, all the way up to the first man. They did all of that by just observing their surroundings and actually paying attention to the land, sea, and sky. You’re gonna tell me that’s not science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thoughts on the mistreatment of Native peoples and do you think there are enough laws out there to protect them in their homelands? — If no, what sorts of things would you like to see protected?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hah. No. Native Hawaiians are at the bottom of every standard there could possibly be. Health, education, incarceration, homelessness, you name it. There is not nearly enough happening to uplift the community. I think part of the problem is that related to the idea of the “vanishing Indian” that the Native people are just going to disappear one day, so let’s just let them? There is also the problem of representation. There is no one of Hawaiian descent in a position of power in the state of Hawaiʻi. Not a single governor or mayor in my lifetime has been Hawaiian. And at the rate we are going, there will be no Hawaiians living in the state to vote for, and once again, there will be a White man in charge of Native lands. We have to do something now or we are screwed. That’s why the fight against TMT is so crucial. It represents so much more than the stupid telescope. It’s about the future of Hawaiians and our land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Off the top of your head is there any other similar controversy that has occurred between science and the Hawaiian culture in the past?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that I know of. But fun fact, the ʻIolani Palace had electricity before the White House. Seems out of character for them to do that considering they are uninnovative and don’t believe in science…&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Question and Answer with Kawai Scanlan</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/images/kawai.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kenedis Q&amp;amp;A</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Kenedi-QnA/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kenedis Q&amp;A" /><published>2021-05-29T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-29T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Kenedi-QnA</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Kenedi-QnA/">&lt;p&gt;My full name is Kenedi Veronica Kapua’enamaikalani Lopes. I am 25% Native Hawaiian ancestry, while the other 75% is comprised of Filipino and Caucasian descent. I graduated from Saint Mary’s College of California with a major in English, and played Division 1 softball for the school. My plan post-undergraduate is to attend UH Manoa’s William Richardson School of Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Living in Hawaii, did you feel any sort of bias against Hawaiians in your own life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up in Hawaii, I was exposed to so many different groups of people. Essentially, this place is a mixing pot of cultures and ethnicities, so it was really nice seeing both familiar and different faces all throughout the islands. Tourists would often disparage my way of speaking pidgin, and that I was the foreigner in my own land. I didn’t speak proper, I didn’t speak as they did, therefore I was incapable and stupid. Inevitably, this made me feel small and contributed to my ill perception of tourists and mainlanders alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you give a little background on your childhood and growing up with the Hawaiian culture?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am comprised of 25% Hawaiian ancestry and for me that quarter percentage is something I value the most, especially when I live on the campus of the only Native Hawaiian boarding school to exist. My mom is a dorm advisor at Kamehameha Schools, so I’ve grown up surrounded by Hawaiian students and mentors all my life. While here, I’ve been exposed to all kinds of cultural traditions—Makahiki games, Hawaiian mele, Kamehameha song contest, imu, hula, etc. While I am not at all fluent in the language, we practice it in our household quite regularly. Being surrounded by the Hawaiian culture has played a significant role in my perception of the world, as I’m keener on empathy and compassion. But due to our history with colonialism, us Hawaiians also keep our guard raised. In celebrating my heritage, it gives me a sense of identity and belonging, so when any part of my culture is uprooted, I feel it is my Kuleana to ensure that it is restored. My parents, aunties, uncles, and grandparents instill within me an appreciation for knowing where we’ve come from and encourage me to know where we need to be going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The thing about TMT that frustrates you the most?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many things that frustrate me when it comes to the dispute on Mauna Kea, but perhaps what is most appalling is that this narrative has been told too many times. This sacred mountain is the birthplace of our Hawaiian culture, an essential part of what makes Hawaiians, Hawaiians. It’s the equivalent to America’s Rushmore or the Bible’s Garden of Eden. For our government to willingly give away the most important and valued piece of land to science without considering how it contributes to the desecration of our culture is ridiculous and infuriating. And it’s all for profit. What it boils down to isn’t science vs. Hawaiians, but a fight for doing the right thing. The Kanaka will not back down from this battle because Mauna Kea is the last thing we have left. We’ve already lost Waikiki to tourism and our once sovereign nation to America, but we are not going to lose our place of birth. You can build a telescope elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thoughts on the mistreatment of Native peoples and do you think there are enough laws out there to protect them in their homelands? — If no, what sorts of things would you like to see protected?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned above, this tale is the oldest story in the book. We’re not the only indigenous group fighting the same fight. And the fact that we even have to think about creating laws to protect homelands because people are too greedy is unfathomable. There are sanctions in place to ensure that Native Hawaiians have a share of the land, like the Hawaiian Homesteads. However, it’s still controlled by the government and some Kupuna pass without ever seeing their chance at obtaining the land that was always theirs to begin with. So, I guess, no, there aren’t enough “laws” in place. But ultimately, any law or otherwise that is put in place always has a loophole. And the government will always find that loophole, so what good will any law do for indigenous peoples?&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Question and Answer with Kenedi Lopes</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/images/ken.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Main Arguments</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Arguments/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Main Arguments" /><published>2021-05-05T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Arguments</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Arguments/">&lt;p&gt;There are many arguments on both sides of the controversy, but we will start with those who support TMT. As expected, many of the arguments are based in science. They state on the TMT &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maunakeaandtmt.org/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; a bunch of facts about the telescope: TMT will be located 500 feet below the summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT’s site has no archaeological shrines or features, no endangered plants, no endangered insects and no burials.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT is not visible from any of the places that people consider the most sacred on the mountain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will use a special reflective aluminum-like coating to reflect the ambient environment and reduce the visibility of the structure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will be visible from just 14 percent of Hawaii Island.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will not impact the aquifer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will leave no waste on the mountain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT is highly energy efficient and will receive its electricity from the electrical grid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will not prevent traditional and customary native Hawaiian practices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will be accessible to everyone on Maunakea.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will pay $1 million in annual lease rent; 80 percent will go to the Office of Maunakea Management for stewardship of the mountain and 20 percent will go to the Office of Hawaiian Affairs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will make an annual contribution of $1 million to The Hawaii Island New Knowledge (THINK) Fund to better prepare Hawaii Island students to master STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering and Math) and to become the workforce for higher paying science and technology jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TMT will form and sustain a $1 million a year Workforce Pipeline Program that will lead to a highly qualified pool of local workers.
 All of these bullet points are positive. For those who visit the site may be easily persuaded that this project is a good idea. From a scientific perspective, the Thirty Meter Telescope would be great, and many discoveries would be made with it. On their site, it gives a few pie charts on who supports them and the ethnicities that support/oppose the construction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data is pretty much as expected, but the question we should ask is, who should get the final say? Though most of the other ethnicities have support as the majority, is it their place to say what gets built on land that isn’t theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TMT site also states that they went through a “lengthy process that was approved by the Court and the State,” which means they went through all legal measures to make sure that they were able to build on the mountain (TMT). If this is the case, what is the issue?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Native Hawaiians are unhappy with this decision to build TMT for a few reasons. An article by Ku’ulei Higashi Kanahele and Davianna Pomaika’i McGregor named “Impacts of Astronomy on Indigenous Customary and Traditional Practices as Evident at Mauna Kea” highlights the concerns about the cultural impact the telescope would have. The article explains that Maunakea is a documented as sacred through chants and other oral history. According to the chang Ka Piko Kaulana O Ka ‘Aina, the mountain was born to the goddess Papahanaumoku (Papa – earth mother) and god Wakea (sky father). They go more in depth into the chant and the story of Maunakea, but the main point they make is that the summit is seen as a connection between the earth and the sky. They say that if there is any sort of change to this realm, it could cause drastic impacts to the island’s climate. Whether you believe this to be true, doesn’t matter to the Hawaiians. This is their culture, and they believe it should be respected. The article goes into the fact that Hawaii has many cultural sites throughout the islands. These cultural sites were established by ancestors and attest to the “supreme sanctity and reverence held for the mountain. (Kanahele, 2)” They also include that these sites include burial sites and altars that were accessed by the Native Hawaiians for cultural and religious purposes. They believe that if the Natives do not have access to the mountain the way that they used to, the families will suffer. They state that “these beliefs and traditions about Mauna Kea are spiritual, cultural, and familial all at once. There is no separation. (Kanahele, 3)”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main objective of this article as stated in their executive summary is “[…] to provide an Indigenous viewpoint centered in Native Hawaiian perspectives on the impacts of the TMT project on the Hawaiian community. (Kanahele, 1)” Though TMT has a solid argument as to why they should build the telescope, I think the question comes down to what matters more? Yes, they spent a lot of money on planning and took all legal precautions, but in the end, whose opinion matters? The controversy is between science and culture. Though the telescope would objectively be good for science, is it a justifiable action if those it is personally affecting don’t want it. What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asokamoto.github.io/407FinalProject/blog/Kawais-QnA/&quot;&gt;Kawai’s Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asokamoto.github.io/407FinalProject/blog/Kenedi-QnA/&quot;&gt;Kenedi’s Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asokamoto.github.io/407FinalProject/blog/TMT-In-The-Eyes-Of-Local-People-in-Hawaii-Opinion/&quot;&gt;TMT Opinion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Overview of the arguments made by both TMT and the Native Hawaiians</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/images/graph.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Analysis on Swanner Article</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Swanners-Article/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analysis on Swanner Article" /><published>2021-05-04T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-04T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Swanners-Article</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Swanners-Article/">&lt;p&gt;In Leandra Swanner’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://online.ucpress.edu/hsns/article-abstract/47/3/293/105817/Instruments-of-Science-or-Conquest-Neocolonialism?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, “Instruments of Science or Conquest? Neocolonialism and Modern American Astronomy,” she explains what neocolonialist science is and why that term is a perfect characterization of the fight that is happening on Maunakea. Swanner argues that science has become an instrument of colonialism and that it should be acknowledged as being so. The gives a great background on the controversy including those involved, the amount of money spent on the project, and the main concerns that the Hawaiians have. She goes in depth into the history of Hawaii and how Maunakea is sacred land and is considered a realm of the gods. She also talks about the potential environmental repercussions that come with building such a large telescope on the site. She has a very powerful quote that she got from one of the Native Hawaiian culture practitioners, where they yelled, “Like snakes you are…to come and desecrate our sacred land…for what? For your greed, to look in the sky? You guys can’t even take care of this place! (Swanner, 295)” This is a shared frustration among those who oppose the telescope. Many of the Hawaiians, as mentioned in previous posts, feel that their rights as Natives have not been protected. This telescope is yet another example of how the government has no regard for the Native culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A point that Swanner makes that we haven’t explicitly talked about is the consequences that come with this type of neocolonialist science as it many times brings on controversy. She states,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Although scientists are understandably reluctant to equate their professional activities with cultural annihilation and typically reject such demonizing characterizations, disminssing this unflattering neocolonialist image of modern science has both ethical and practical consequences: Native communities continue to report feeling victimized while scientists’ efforts to expand their research programs suffer social, legal, and economic setbacks. (Swanner, 296)”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important to note as I don’t see either side backing down “peacefully.” It’s unlikely that the Hawaiians will “give up” as this telescope has been described as the “last straw.” I don’t think that TMT will surrender because of all the money they have put into the project and many of them truly don’t think they’re doing anything wrong. They have also said that Maunakea is the best place in the world for this telescope. There really doesn’t seem to be a solution where both parties are happy.
	Swanner also talks a little about the history of astronomy and how previously, they had never felt the need to justify projects to the public as astronomy is seen as a “noble scientific discipline engaged in the pursuit of pure knowledge. (Swanner, 298)” She even explains that astronomers thought that moving the telescope to the sacred mountain would be a “simple” matter. It is all about what they feel is more important. They don’t see the sacred mountain being as important as a telescope. There was a different opinion by the astronomers on Maui, who were surprised by how quickly the telescopes were being built on the mountain because they understood its importance to the Hawaiian culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swanner has a great amount of background information on all aspects of the TMT controversy and concludes that the protesting cannot be dismissed as a one-time surge of opposition or reduced to the hyperbole of science vs. religion. She says “this grassroots anti-observatory campaign epitomizes a larger cultural divide that is historically anchored to the rise of environmental and Native rights movements in the United States as well as competing scientific and spiritual narratives. (Swanner, 316)” She also claims that astronomers’ narratives have not changed over the past few decades and most of their projects do not take Native rights into consideration; they instead only look at the financials and logistics. She explains that astronomers are needing to adapt to the new world where others want a say in what they do. Before, there was no question as to whether their projects were valid, but now they’re needing to justify themselves more than ever. In the case of the telescope, she claims that it is an instrument of power and conquest, and a symbol of cultural genocide linked to a colonialist past (Swanner, 318). She finished with stating that the future of astronomy will depend on astronomer’s acceptance of the “role of colonialism in shaping hierarchical and racialized understandings of Native peoples, nature, and technology. (Swanner, 318)”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asokamoto.github.io/407FinalProject/blog/Arguments/&quot;&gt;Main Arguments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title type="html">Neocolonialism and Colonialism in Hawaii</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Neocolonialism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neocolonialism and Colonialism in Hawaii" /><published>2021-05-03T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-03T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Neocolonialism</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Neocolonialism/">&lt;p&gt;Going forward, it is important that we have a general understanding of colonialism, neocolonialism and its effects on Hawaii. 
Colonialism is described as “the deliberate imposition of the rules and policies of a nation on another nation. (Fieser, Dowden)” This is used as a way to exploit the colonized nation to facilitate economic development in the home state. The main concept of colonialism is that with rule over another country or region, the conqueror’s country will benefit from the exploitation of the conquered resources. When a state is conquered, their economic, political, social and sometimes intellectual structure is altered due to the influence of the conqueror. “Neocolonialism” is a term that describes the actions and effects that are left from the days of the colonial era in a society (Fieser, Dowden). Though we aren’t seeing as much colonialism in the 21st century, we are seeing the remanence of the colonial era as neocolonialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not many are taught about the annexation of Hawaii and are surprised to find that it was an illegal act. At the time, the head of the Kingdom of Hawaii was Queen Lili`uokalani. In 1893, she was overthrown by American businessmen and placed under house arrest for months. This was in efforts to get better military position for the United States. Below is a video by PBS Hawaii on the injustice she faced as Queen that should be watched as it gives background information on the illegal overthrow of the Hawaiian government. When royalists tried to restore the Queen’s position as queen, she was arrested and put on trial. She was convicted and sentenced to five years in prison at hard labor, and fined $5,000. This was eventually reduced to house arrest in a room at Iolani Palace for eight months. More can be learned at the Iolani Palace &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iolanipalace.org/history/queens-imprisonment/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some argue that Hawaii is still being illegally occupied by the United States as the annexation was done was unlawfully and as an aggressive act of war. After the overthrow, the teaching of the Hawaiian language was banned and those who spoke it in school, were punished (Sang). This would continue for the next four generations. This was in efforts to silence the Hawaiian culture and move toward more “western” culture and traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this day, Hawai’i is seen as a tourist destination and those who visit usually have no knowledge of its history. It’s a touchy subject as there were many consequences from this era. This is an important concept to understand before going into the TMT controversy as many arguments from the Native Hawaiians are based on the lack of respect that outsiders have for the native culture. If you ask around in Hawaii, the local people often despise tourists, “haole” as they call them. This is not only because they have little respect for the land, but they also have no knowledge of what conspired in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of this lack of respect for the land, there is currently a big controversy surrounding &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrattorneys.com/blog/zuckerbergs-hawaii-estate-new-face-of-neocolonialism/&quot;&gt;Mark Zuckerberg’s Hawaii estate&lt;/a&gt; as he is attempting to purchase protected land around his already large $100 million Kauai property. The protected land are Hawaiian land parcels which are reserved for the natives. Mr. Zuckerberg is trying to take that land from the native Hawaiians, which seems to be a trend in Hawaiian history. It is events like these that show us that neocolonialism is still present today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hawaii.pbslearningmedia.org/resource/ha06.ush.ind.overthrow/the-overthrow-of-queen-liliuokalani/&quot;&gt;PBS Video on Annexation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asokamoto.github.io/407FinalProject/blog/Swanners-Article/&quot;&gt;Swanner Article Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhcohawaii.org/sermons/w-3-29-20-the-queens-meet-the-king/&quot;&gt;image link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Background information on colonialism and neocolonilism in Hawaii</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/images/queenLiliuokalani.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Annotated Bibliography</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Bibliography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Annotated Bibliography" /><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-02T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Bibliography</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Bibliography/">&lt;p&gt;Central Material&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swanner, Leandra. “Instruments of Science or Conquest? Neocolonialism and Modern American Astronomy.” Historical Studies in the Natural Sciences 47, no. 3 (June 1, 2017): 293–319. https://doi.org/10.1525/hsns.2017.47.3.293.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;This paper by Leandra Swanner gives a great background on the controversy behind the construction of the telescope on Mauna Kea. She talks about how modern American astronomy has changed over the years moving into the public eye and also argues that “the TMT debate can best be understood as an exemplar of what [she] refer(s) to as ‘neocolonialist science’. (296)” She goes deeply into how Western science needs to come to terms with the role it has on Native peoples, nature and technology. This is great for this project as it gives base knowledge of the (Native) Hawaiian culture needed for this topic along with background information on the astronomy “culture”.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aanchal, Saraf. “‘We’d Rather Eat Rocks’: Contesting the Thirty Meter Telescope in a Struggle over Science and Sovereignty in Hawai`i.” 2020, n.d. https://escholarship.org/uc/item/70z6w502.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;This paper by Saraf Aanchal will be used to talk about the history of science in Hawaii and astronomy. This is an important aspect to the controversy that not a lot of people know about. I think it’s crucial that people understand this history because it gives more background as to why the Hawaiians are upset and it also goes into the difference between “traditional” and “western” science. I do reference one of the papers we read earlier in the term (Redrawing the Map by Fa-ti Fan) because there is a similar theme here with binaries in science. Aacnchal talks about how there is a history of science there that is being disregarded because of its roots in native culture. In order to fully understand the Hawaiians arguments, readers need to know about their prior knowledge of the stars and astronomy.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting Material&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bartels, Meghan. “The Thirty Meter Telescope: How a Volcano in Hawaii Became a Battleground for Astronomy.” The Thirty Meter Telescope: How a Volcano in Hawaii Became a Battleground for Astronomy (blog), n.d. https://www.space.com/thirty-meter-telescope-hawaii-volcano-maunakea-opposition.html.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fieser, James, Dowden, Bradley. “Neocolonialism.” Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy. Accessed May 21, 2021. https://iep.utm.edu/neocolon/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Home.” Maunakea &amp;amp; TMT. September 25, 2020. Accessed May 10, 2021. https://www.maunakeaandtmt.org/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;This is the home page to the Maunakea &amp;amp; TMT site. There is a lot of great background information on this website.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopes, Kenedi, n.d.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;This will be an interview with my friend Kenedi, who is a Native Hawaiian. She grew up living at Kamehameha Schools, which is a Native Hawaiian school in Hawaii. She is deeply integrated into the Hawaiian culture. I want to get her view on the controversy as someone who is from Hawaii and also has a Native Hawaiian background.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ngyuen, Frances. “The Pandemic Hasn’t Stopped Native Hawaiians’ Fight to Protect Maunakea,” August 7, 2020. https://www.vox.com/2020/8/7/21354619/mauna-kea-tmt-telescope-native-hawaiians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Person. “The Devastating Effects of Colonization on Hawai’i.” ArcGIS StoryMaps. July 27, 2019. Accessed May 22, 2021. https://storymaps.arcgis.com/stories/83474c5d6077492d990b961bab0bcd74.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PBS Hawai’i. “The Overthrow of Queen Lili`uokalani,” n.d. https://hawaii.pbslearningmedia.org/resource/ha06.ush.ind.overthrow/the-overthrow-of-queen-liliuokalani/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sang, Kau’i. “Hawaii DOE: History of Hawaiian Education.” Hawaii DOE | History of Hawaiian Education. Accessed May 22, 2021. https://www.hawaiipublicschools.org/TeachingAndLearning/StudentLearning/HawaiianEducation/Pages/History-of-the-Hawaiian-Education-program.aspx&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scanlan, Kawaiuluhonua, n.d.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;This will be an interview with my friend Kawai, who is a Native Hawaiian. She is a recent graduate where she majored in both psychology and Native American studies. Her focus is on Native Hawaiians and intends to go to law school. I want to get her view on the controversy as someone with her educational and personal background.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><summary type="html">Annotated bibliography of websites and articles mentioned on this website.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Science and Astronomy in Hawaii</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Science-and-Astronomy-in-Hawaii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science and Astronomy in Hawaii" /><published>2021-05-02T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-02T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Science-and-Astronomy-in-Hawaii</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/Science-and-Astronomy-in-Hawaii/">&lt;p&gt;The Disney movie Moana is a heartwarming story about a young princess who teams up with the Hawaiian Demi-god Maui in order to save her home, Motonui, by restoring the heart of Te Fiti, the goddess of creation. In order to do this, she needs to learn how to navigate the ocean using the stars and make her way to Te Fiti’s island. Though animated movies like this are mostly fiction, the creators of Moana had to do some research on the art of wayfinding. Polynesians have been navigating the ocean since 300 A.D., which is how they were able to make their initial migration across the Pacific without modern technology. Celestial navigation, or wayfinding, was once a forgotten tradition, but Polynesians have since revitalized the practice in the creation of the Hokule’a ship. The double-hulled boat is modeled after the original boats that the Polynesians sailed all those years ago. The boat made its way from Hawaii to Tahiti by only use of wayfinding in 1976. Since then, the Hokule’a has made 11 voyages and completed their longest worldwide 6-year trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Saraf’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/70z6w502&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, “’We’d rather eat rocks’: Contesting the Thirty Meter Telescope in a Struggle over Science and Sovereignty in Hawai’i,” she explains that Western scientists have historicized the Native Hawaiians as ancient astronomers. She says that this would suggest they are stuck in the past and the “expansiveness of their practice is reduced and retrofitted in the service of a colonial narrative. (Saraf, 152)” She thinks that the most concerning part of this is that this reduction implies that this ancient art of wayfinding ends with the invention of Western astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saraf argues that the settlers (those who are not native to Hawaii) who represent the TMT are using a strategy of sovereignty denial that is rooted in “undermining [Native Hawaiian] ontologies and epistemologies. (Saraf, 154)” in their arguments to build the telescope. She says that supporters are calling the Hawaiians “anti-science,” while simultaneously excluding their worldviews from carrying the same weight of intellectual likeness to Western knowledge production. To summarize, Saraf explains that settlers expect the Native Hawaiians to comply with their way of life. They expect a certain amount of predictability from the Natives that when they don’t act in an expected way, they categorize it as opposition. In this case, the Native Hawaiians claiming the land as sacred and protesting the construction forces the settlers to perceive this behavior as anti-scientific primitivism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a trend we see in science when we compare “western” vs. “traditional.” Earlier in the term, we read an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/521156&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; by Fa-ti Fan, “Redrawing the Map.” There was a similar concept in this paper where Fan talks about how these binaries (such as western vs. traditional) can be detrimental to the overall view of a country’s science. Much of China’s science has been labeled “traditional,” which many times will translate to being unreliable or not as reliable as “western” science. This is not the case and that can be seen here in the Hawaiian culture’s astronomy. There is valid science behind wayfinding, and it works, but because it wasn’t created by a “western” power, it is dismissed as inaccurate. This is a problem that has been occurring across all non-western science and has its roots in colonialism and neocolonialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asokamoto.github.io/407FinalProject/blog/Neocolonialism/&quot;&gt;Colonialism and Neocolonialism in Hawaii&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Analysis on Aanchal Saraf's paper</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TMT Controversy Background Information</title><link href="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/TMT-Controversy-Background/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TMT Controversy Background Information" /><published>2021-05-01T00:00:00-10:00</published><updated>2021-05-01T00:00:00-10:00</updated><id>asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/TMT-Controversy-Background</id><content type="html" xml:base="asokamoto.github.io/407finalproj/blog/TMT-Controversy-Background/">&lt;p&gt;Maunakea, an extinct volcano on the Big Island of Hawaii has been a hub for telescopes since the first one was built in 1979. It is currently the world’s largest astronomical observatories and over the past 40 years, a total of 13 telescopes have been built. Though the summit is loved by scientists due to its prime location, it is also considered sacred to the Native Hawaiians. In 2015, the Thirty Meter Telescope (TMT) was approved to be built on top Maunakea, which sparked an uproar by Hawaiians around the globe. Previously, Natives had unsuccessfully stopped construction of telescopes upon their sacred mountain, but when they found out the scale of the newest project, they decided that enough was enough. 
TMT would be 18 stories tall with structures extending over 1.44 acres, which is much larger than any of the current telescopes built there. In terms of scientific research, TMT would allow astronomers to see 13 billion light-years away and scientists believe that it would give great insight into why we are on Earth and what else is out in the galaxy. Though the project would objectively be great for science, the question is, at what cost? Those who oppose TMT are unsettled both by the blatant disregard for the Native culture and brings to light the colonization that has taken place in Hawaii. 
I will talk about both the TMT supporter’s and opposer’s arguments in depth in the linked blog posts below, but first we should discuss the history of science and astronomy within the Hawaiian culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asokamoto.github.io/407FinalProject/blog/Science-and-Astronomy-in-Hawaii/&quot;&gt;Science and Astonomy in Hawaii – Saraf’s Paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">Background information on the TMT controversy</summary></entry></feed>
